Guide to the Pittsburgh Club Records, 1880-1995 AIS.1971.09
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Club Records
1880-1995
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Club
AIS.1971.09
3.75 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The Pittsburgh Club began in 1879 as a social club for businessmen in downtown Pittsburgh. This collection consists of several volumes meeting minutes, scrapbooks, club artifacts, and photographs. Digital reproductions of selected material is available online.
History
The Pittsburgh Club was founded on April 5, 1879 by a group of men who were dissatisfied with their treatment at Pittsburgh's Duquesne Club. They met at the law office of George W. Guthrie, later Mayor of Pittsburgh and United States Ambassador to Japan, to create a constitution, formulate rules of their club house, and build a committee structure. The membership throughout the Club's history included: industrialist, bankers, attorneys, merchants, and a variety of other professionals that dominated the business and professional classes of Pittsburgh.
The first Club house was located at 259 Penn Avenue in downtown Pittsburgh. The Club remained in that location for about a decade when they relocated to 425 Penn Avenue, to a mansion that was formerly the home of the John Schoenberger family. In the pre-Civil War years, Penn Avenue was the residential neighborhood where many of Pittsburgh's affluent citizens lived. Following the end of the war, many of these affluent residents began moving across the Allegheny River to Allegheny City and to Pittsburgh's East End neighborhoods (such as East Liberty, Shadyside and Squirrel Hill) as the downtown district was becoming the center of business and commerce. The Schoenberger house remained the headquarters for the club until 1942, when they relocated to rented space at the William Penn Hotel.
Membership rolls include the names of many well-known individuals, such as: Richard King Mellon, Andrew W. Mellon, William L. Mellon, Arthur Vining Davis, Joseph Horne, George Westinghouse, Charles L. McCune, Benjamin F. Jones, George Laughlin, James Verner Scaife, William B. Scaife, Alan M. Scaife, Roy A. Hunt, Thomas J. Hilliard, James F. Hillman, Howard Heinz, C. B. Shea, Henry O. Rea, and Dr. Stanley Rinehardt.
In 1937, a Women's Committee was formed, marking for the first time the eligibility of women to join the club. In later years as women who held professional positions as attorneys, accountants and corporate officers would be listed as full members of the club.
The Club celebrated it centennial in 1979. A history of the organization was written by members Charles Lockhart and John Creighton and the celebration received lengthy coverage in the newspapers. However, the membership of the organization slowly declined. In 1997, the Pittsburgh Club merged with the Harvard-Yale-Princeton (HYP) Club and moved out of the William Penn Hotel and into the HYP quarters at 619 William Penn Place. The merged organization became known as the HYP-Pittsburgh Club. An additional merger took place in 2004 between the Allegheny Club (formerly located at Three Rivers Stadium) and the HYP-Pittsburgh Club. The organization dropped "Pittsburgh" from its name at that time and is known as the Allegheny-HYP Club.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection includes volumes of meeting minutes from from 1891 to 1936, membership directories, club correspondence, newspaper clippings, annual financial statements, artifacts, and photographs.
Access Restrictions
Membership Applications that dated from the late 20th century often include social security numbers. Researchers accessing these files must complete a CONFIDENTIALITY AGREEMENT form at the Reference Desk.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Pittsburgh Club in 1971. Additions were made by Mr. Robert Gates (last president of the Pittsburgh Club) in 2002.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh Club Records, 1880-1995, AIS.1971.09, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the membership directories are scanned and available online.
Arrangement
The records are arranged with the following series designations:
Series I: Assorted Records
Series II: Oversized Materials
Series III: Realia [Artifacts]
Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social life and customs; Societies; Clubs -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh Club
- Assorted Records, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Assorted Records Series includes: minutes, legal documents, printed rosters, membership records, financial records, historical sketches and anniversary programs, clippings, and a variety of menu's.
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Billiard Room Repairs and Improvements, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Governors, Assorted Notes, 1938-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Governors, Minute Book, 1891-1900 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Board of Governors, Minute Book, 1900-1920 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Board of Governors, Minutes, 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Governors, Minutes, 1924-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Governors, Minutes, 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board of Governors, Minutes, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board of Governors, Minutes, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Governors, Minutes, 1944-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board of Governors, Minutes, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of Governors, Minutes, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bylaws, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Christmas Fund Distribution, 1922-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clippings and Articles [regarding Club History], 1942-1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Constitution, c1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Constitution, Rules, and House Rules, Recordbook, 1880-1894 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Constitution, Rules, and Rosters (Booklets), 1904-1941 (Box 1, Volume 14-19)
  - Correspondence (General), 1922-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence [regarding membership], 1975-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2-12)
  - Federal Tax Return, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Financial Records, 1924-1942 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Financial Situation (Sale of Club House), 1942 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Financial Statements, 1956-1984 (Box 2, Folder 16-19)
  - Fine Art Appraisal by J. J. Gillespie Co., 1942 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - History of the Pittsburgh Club 1879-1979, by Charles Lockhart and John Creighton, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Inventory and Appraisal of Furniture and Fixtures by Earle Gosser, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Membership Applications [RESTRICTED ACCESS], 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Membership Applications, Regular Members [RESTRICTED ACCESS], 1962-1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Membership Applications, Senior Members [RESTRICTED ACCESS], 1953-1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Membership Applications, Graduate Members [RESTRICTED ACCESS], 1962-1992 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Memberhsip Applications, Non-Resident Members [RESTRICTED ACCESS], 1965-1992 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Membership Applications, Resigned Members [RESTRICTED ACCESS], 1949-80 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Membership Roster, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Menu's, Pittsburgh Club, 1942-1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Menu's, William Penn Hotel, c1940 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - One Hundred Tenth Anniversary, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Plan of Reorganization, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Retailer's License under Beverage License Law (Application), c1930 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Roster of Club Officials, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Scrapbook of Club mailings and cards, 1928-1939 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Sixtieth Anniversary, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Sixty-Fifth Anniversary (Club History), 1944 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Thirtieth Anniversary, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Wine List, Duquesne Club, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Wine List & Beverage List, Pittsburgh Club, c1940-1993 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Women's Committee, c1950 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Oversized Material, II.
  The Oversized Materials include: architectural drawings of the Club's quarters at the William Penn Hotel, a recordbook of candidates fro membership, drawings of the Club facility on Penn Avenue, and a photograph of the 30th annual banquet.
  - Architectural Drawings of Club Suite at the William Penn Hotel (3 sheets By J. Phillips Davis), 1942 (Map-case 32-7, Folder 1)
  - Candidates for Membership, 1903-1939 (Map-case 32-7, Volume 1)
  - Drawing of the Penn Avenue Club house: main entrance with banner, undated (Map-case 32-7, Folder 2)
  - Drawing of the Penn Avenue Club house, ladies entrance, undated (Map-case 32-7, Folder 3)
  - Drawing of the Penn Avenue Club house: sitting room, undated (Map-case 32-7, Folder 4)
  - Thirtieth Anniversary Banquet, Photograph by Johnston, 1909 (Map-case 32-7, Folder 5)
- Realia [Artifacts], undated; III.
  The Realia Series includes 9 artifacts from the Club's history, including: ballot boxes, gaming paraphernalia, a candlestick holder and a Prohibition era sign.
  - Ballot Box (with 19 white balls & 6 black balls), undated (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Ballot Box (with lock), undated (Box 3, Item 2)
  - Candlestick holder (engraved "Pittsburg Club" on the bottom, electroplate by Gorham), undated (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Corporate Seal and Embosser (with fabric case), undated (Box 4, Item 4)
  - Dice Tumbler (engraved "Pittsburgh Club" silver cup by Meriden Britannia Company within a leather tumbler), undated (Box 3, Item 5)
  - Dice (1 green die and 1 white die), undated (Box 3, Item 6)
  - 18th Amendment "Prohibition" Sign, (framed), 1920 (Box 3, Item 7)
  - Game Box (wooden, with a latch), undated (Box 3, Item 8)
  - Poker Chips (Blue, Red, Green, White, Yellow), undated (Box 4, Item 9)